Guide to the Lockwood Sanford Wood Engraving Proof Books 1938-1913 (Bulk 1880-1904) PR 247
New-York Historical Society
Lockwood Sanford Wood Engraving Proof Books
1838-1913 (Bulk 1880-1904)
New-York Historical Society
PR 247
2.29 Linear feet (6 boxes)
Wood engravings produced for business advertisements, mostly in and around New Haven, Connecticut.
Provenance
Puchase, 1936.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Biographical Note
Lockwood Sanford (1817-1890) was born in Naugatuck, CT. He moved to New Haven in 1837 and became apprenticed to engraver E. L. Barber. Sanford and Barber formed a partnership in 1843. In 1847, Barber moved to California, and Sanford continued his business on his own. Sanford specialized in wood engraving used to supplement billheads, price sheets, circulars, and other publications printed by local industries, both manufacturing concerns and retail stores. Sanford's son Frederick was working in the business at the time of his father's death, and continued working as a wood engraver at least until 1913
Scope and Content Note
The Lockwood Sanford Wood Engraving Proof Books span the period from 1838 to 1913 and contains compilation books with examples of the kinds of wood engravings Sanford created during his career. The majority of these images were used to print price lists or circulars issued by businesses in New Haven, CT and surrounding cities.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into two series:
Missing Title
Client Sample Books
Scrapbooks
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Wood engravings by Lockwood Sanford can be found throughout the Bella C. Landauer Collection of Business and Advertising Ephemera (PR 031), where they are filed by type of business.
Wood engravings.; New Haven (Conn.); Scrapbooks.; Advertisements.
- Series I: Client Sample Books
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. includes fifty-four small books (some hand bound with twine) in which samples of wood engravings done for Sanford's clients are pasted, along with the date done (or perhaps the date paid) and the price for each engraving. The engravings date from 1874 to 1910. The books generally show products sold by each client, but also occasionally include letterhead, cuts of factory buildings, business cards, and corporate identifications. Most books date from over a period of years, sometimes allowing the change in models and products sold by businesses to be measured.
  The books in this series all measure approximately 9 x 6 inches. The client sample books are arranged alphabetically by client. Client names are written on the exterior of each book; it is sometimes the case that proofs for more than client can be found in one book. In this case, all clients have been listed in the following container list. Where a location of the business has been determined, it is noted in the container list.
  - Andrew B. Hendryx Company, New Haven, 1878-1892 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Bird cages, iron bed, fishing reels, wire picture cord, gears (1 book)
  - B. Shoninger Company, New Haven, 1881-1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    Organs (1 book)
  - B. D. Druen, New Haven (Offsite-box 1, Folder unknown container)
    See: James Pendergast Company
  - Barnes Manufacturing Company, New Haven, 1881-1896 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    Locks, keys (1 book)
  - Beecher & Peck, New Haven Miner & Peck Manufacturing Company, New Haven, 1878-1891 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    Drop hammers, tools (1 book)
  - Bigelow Company, New Haven, 1878-1887 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    Steam boilers (1 book)
  - Blake and Johnson William A. Ives, 1880-1887 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    Machines and tools (1 book)
  - Boston Buckboard Company, New Haven, 1880-1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    Carriages (1 book)
  - D. Frisbie and Company, New Haven, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    Machines (1 book)
  - Dann Brothers & Company, New Haven, 1876-1910 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    Coach and carriage equipment (1 book)
  - Derby Silver Company, Derby, 1879 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    Table settings (1 book)
  - E. Crisand, 1882 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    Overshoes (1 book)
  - E.D. Clapp Manufacturing Company, Auburn, NY, 1880-1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    Carriage equipment (1 book)
  - Edwin J. Toof, New Haven, 1881-1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    Sewing machine attachments (1 book)
  - Edson Sanford, 1878-1881 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    Vases, teapots, lamps, belt buckles (1 book)
  - English & Mersick Company, New Haven New Haven Folding Chair Company, New Haven, 1877-1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    Carriage equipment, wheel chairs (1 book)
  - G.B. Sheldon P.T. Ives, Wallingford, 1877-1892 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    Nails, hinges, miscellaneous pharmacy (1 book)
  - George B. Hoggson, 1881-1887 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    Matches, pipes (1 book)
  - H.D. Smith & Company, 1876-1885 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
    Carriage equipment (2 books)
  - H.P. Hubbard, New Haven, 1878-1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    Printer's supplies, printing presses (1 book)
  - Hayden and Boyd Hayden and Smith, 1878-1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
    Wagon equipment (1 book)
  - I.E. Palmer, Middletown, 1886-1895 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
    Hammocks, rope fasteners (1 book)
  - J.M. Marlin, 1877-1888 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
    Guns, handcuffs (1 book)
  - James Pendergast Company, New Haven B. D. Druen, 1879-1910 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
    Carriage steps and hardware (2 books)
  - John Adt & Son, New Haven, 1882-1889 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
    Lathes (2 books)
  - L. Candee and Company, New Haven, 1881-1885 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
    Rubber boots, shoes (1 book)
    See also: Punderson
  - M. Seward & Sons Company, New Haven, 1875-1887 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
    Iron bolts, fasteners (1 book)
  - Miner & Peck Manufacturing Company, New Haven (Box Unknown container 578 for instance of Miner & Peck Manufacturing Company, New Haven, Folder unknown container)
    See: Beecher & Peck
  - Monson & Company, New Haven, 1879-1887 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
    Pharmacy and dry goods (1 book)
  - Mutual Rubber Company (Box Unknown container 579 for instance of Mutual Rubber Company, Folder unknown container)
    See: Punderson
  - Nelson W. Twiss, New Haven, 1876-1886 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
    Machines and engines (1 book)
  - New Haven Folding Chair Company, New Haven, 1879-1891 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29)
    Portable parlor chairs, invalid reclining and rolling chairs (1 book)
    See also: English & Mersick
  - New Haven Manufacturing Company, New Haven, 1875-1889 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 30)
    Machine tools, lathes (1 book)
  - New Haven Rattan Company, New Haven, 1890-1891 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 31)
    Baby carriages, chairs (1 book)
  - O. B. North and Company, New Haven, 1876-1886 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 32)
    Carriage hardware (2 books)
  - P.T. Ives, Wallingford (Box Unknown container 580 for instance of P.T. Ives, Wallingford, Folder unknown container)
    See: G.B. Sheldon
  - Peck Brothers & Company, New Haven, 1876-1886 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
    Brass faucets, plumbing fixtures (2 books)
  - Punderson Mutual Rubber Company L. Candee & Company, New Haven, 1885-1888 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34)
    Boots, overshoes (2 books)
  - Sallader, 1883-1885 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
  - Simpson, Hall, Miller, New Haven, 1878 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 36)
    Silverplated household cutlery (1 book)
  - Southington Cut Company, 1888-1889 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 37)
    Pocketknives (1 book)
  - Sperry Manufacturing Company, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
    Iron equipment (1 book)
  - Sweetland & Company, New Haven, 1882-1887 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 39)
  - Union Metallic Cartridge Company, Bridgeport, 1882-1887 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
    Cartridges, bullets (1 book)
  - W. & E. T. Fitch Company, New Haven, 1886 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 41)
    Iron castings (1 book)
  - Whitney Arms Company, New Haven, 1874-1887 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 42)
    Rifles, handguns, cartridges (1 book)
  - Wilcox and Howe, 1885-1886 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 43)
    Machines, tools (1 book)
  - William Lyman, 1884-1887 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 44)
    Rifles (1 book)
  - Winchester Repeating Arms Co, New Haven, 1878-1887 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 45)
    Rifles, cartridges (2 books)
  - Youngstown Malliable Iron Company, 1884 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 46)
    Rings, hooks (1 book)
  - Blank client sample book, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 47)
- Series II: Scrapbooks
  Series II. holds sixteen compilation books of engravings, proofs, drawings, and invoices which were glued randomly in commercial books. One of these books was removed from the Album File, where it had been listed separately as an album (formerly PR-002-238). The material is not arranged in either client or chronological order. The work is largely unsigned. The engravings found inside date from 1838-1913. The bound volume in Box 4 includes an engraving marked "first engraving, 25th June 1838." The notebooks into which most of the proofs have been pasted were produced by Whitlock's Bookstore in New Haven; they are student workbooks for reading course, and are copyrighted in 1924, so that somewhat dates their creation. Frederick Sanford or another family member must have pasted in these engravings sometime after 1924.
  - Bound volume, vignettes and animal scenes, many signed "L.S.", undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 48)
  - Bound volume, seals for societies, companies, notaries, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 49)
  - Bound volume, vignettes (with prices), landscapes, advertising, scientific diagrams, 1838-ca. 1866 (Offsite-box 4, Folder unknown container)
  - Notebook, screws, corsets, matches, rifles, seed packets, invoices, envelopes addressed to Sanford laid in, 1882-1891 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 50)
  - Notebook, strike plates, carriages, door hardware, hooks and eyes, match boxes, labels, hairpins, invoices, 1872-1908 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 51)
  - Notebook, clocks, clock faces, nursery stock, hairpins, pharmacy products, pipe coil, 1882-1898 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 52)
  - Notebook, fasteners, clock faces, machinery, tools, medical illustrations, invoices, 1868-1903 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 53)
  - Notebook, tobacco, pins, maps, scientific drawings, pharmacy products, fasteners, 1879-1904 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 54)
  - Notebook, pins, fasteners, tools, shoes, 1880-1906 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 55)
  - Notebook, machines, nails, maps, lamps, invoices, 1882-1895 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 56)
  - Notebook, tools, metal products, hardware, signatures, trademarks and logos, animals, 1877-1914 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 57)
  - Notebook, machines, vignettes, corsets, knives, 1880-1894 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 58)
  - Notebook, machinery, tools, chairs, furniture, shears, calling cards, maps, 1877-1897 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 59)
  - Notebook, clocks, shears, dress forms, metal products, ammunition, tools, invoices, 1872-1900 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 60)
  - Notebook, hairpins, sewing machine parts, carriages, fishing reels, 1873-1913 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 61)
  - Notebook, flatware, rifles, machines, tools, scientific illustrations, 1880-1897 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 62)